{"tossups": [{"question": "A former member of the Connecticut General Assembly stumbled across a river in this state in 1796, finding a site to found a city along it. That river in this state was described as a body that\u201coozes rather than flows\u201d by TIME magazine after an incident that helped lead to the creation of its state\u2019s Environmental Protection Agency. For ten points, name this state, the first state created from the Northwest Territory and the site of a 1969 fire on the Cuyahoga River.", "answer": "<em><b> Ohio</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event was nationally confirmed by the Decree of 16 Pluviose after a delegation including Jean-Baptiste Belley arrived in the National Assembly. Leger-Felicite Sonthonax proclaimed this event hoping to gain allies, although it failed to immediately sway Toussaint Louverture. Reinstated in 1848 after being undone by Napoleon in 1802, for ten points, what is this event that began in the colony of Saint-Domingue?", "answer": "<em><b> Abolition</b></em> in<em><b> France</b></em> (accept answers indicating the ending of slavery in<em><b> France</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This character disguises himself using Erpingham\u2019s cloak before exchanging gloves with the soldier Michael Williams. At the siege of Harfleur, this man delivers a speech that begins \u201conce more unto the breach dear friends.\u201d This king claims that \u201cif it be a sin to covet honour, / [he is] the most offending soul alive\u201d as he addresses a \u201cband of brothers\u201d on St. Crispin\u2019s Day. For ten points, name this Shakespearean king who wins the Battle of Agincourt.", "answer": "<em><b> Henry V</b></em> (accept<em><b> Henry of Monmouth</b></em>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "During this election year, the winning party held its convention at the Chicago \u201cWigwam.\u201d At the losing party\u2019s convention in Baltimore in this year, many \u201cFire-Eaters\u201d expressed disapproval with the party platform. John Bell\u2019s Constitutional Union Party ran in this year, which also featured Vice-President John Breckinridge among two Democratic nominees from the North and South. For ten points, name this presidential election year in which Abraham Lincoln won his first term.", "answer": "<em><b> 1860</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This battle is commemorated by a memorial complex on the heights of Mamayev Kurgan including the grave of Marshal Vasily Chuikov. A statue designed by Yevgeny Vuchetich is part of that complex and depicts a woman holding a sword. Asger Jorn\u2019s painting of this battle shows soldiers of the German Sixth Army covered in snow. For ten points, name this battle, commemorated by the 85-meter tall The Motherland Calls, the decisive Eastern Front battle of World War Two.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Stalingrad</b></em> Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The North Adams strike at a factory making these objects was broken up by Chinese strikebreakers in Boston. One incident involving this kind of object occurred after Filipino diplomat Lorenzo Sumulong criticized restrictions of human rights in Eastern Europe. Iraqi journalist Muntadhar al-Zaidi threw one of these at George W. Bush during a press conference. For ten points, name this type of object, one of which was banged against a podium by Nikita Khrushchev at the UN General Assembly.", "answer": "A<em><b> shoe</b></em> (accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of this woman\u2019s best known songs was written for a 1980 movie she starred in that highlights male chauvinism in the workplace. This woman\u2019s philanthropic efforts include giving away more than 100 million books to promote literacy as well as supporting AIDS research. This musician gained attention in 2020 for donating one million dollars towards Moderna\u2019s COVID-19 vaccine research. For ten points, name this country singer-songwriter known for the song and movie \u201c9 to 5.\u201d", "answer": "Dolly<em><b> Parton</b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s first major newspaper was founded during Reconstruction as the Democratic Statesman and was later renamed as the American-Statesman. Huston-Tillotson University was the first historically black college in this city. Another university in this city was where Charles Whitman opened fire on a crowd from that university\u2019s namesake tower. For ten points, name this city, where the University of Texas was founded.", "answer": "<em><b> Austin</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man claimed that he would have carried out a series of sniper attacks if the book Unintended Consequences was written a few years earlier. Charles Fortier was an associate of this man who distributed copies of the Turner Diaries at gun shows. Revenge for the ATF siege of the Branch Davidian compound in Waco, Texas was one of the key motivations of this man\u2019s attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Building in 1995. For ten points, name this perpetrator of the Oklahoma City bombing.", "answer": "Timothy<em><b> McVeigh</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man once defined fascism as \u201cnothing but capitalist reaction\u201d and argued that a state of\u201cpermanent revolution\u201d was better than a rival\u2019s idea of \u201csocialism in one country.\u201d Seven years after his exile, this man published The Revolution Betrayed which analyzed the Soviet Union following the death of Vladimir Lenin. This man served as military commissar during the Russian Civil War, for which he created the Red Army. For ten points, name this Russian revolutionary opposed to Stalin.", "answer": "Leon<em><b> Trotsky</b></em> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man appeased his rivals by issuing the Dictum of Kenilworth. Though this man had been defeated at Taillebourg by Louis IX, Louis supported this ruler against the nobility in the Mise of Amiens. This ruler was captured at the Battle of Lewes by rebel forces, though he was freed after his son\u2019s victory at Evesham against Simon de Montfort in the Second Baron\u2019s War. For ten points, name this father of Edward Longshanks who signed away part of his power in the Provisions of Oxford.", "answer": "<em><b> Henry III</b></em> (accept<em><b> Henry of Winchester</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This movement\u2019s founder spread his teachings door-to-door in Detroit and Chicago, and this organization holds its Saviour\u2019s Day event on that man\u2019s birthday. This movement\u2019s official newspaper is the Chicago based Final Call. Chicago is also home to the Mosque Maryam, which serves as this movement\u2019s headquarters. This movement was founded in 1932 by Wallace Fard Muhammad. For ten points, name this Black religious movement, led after 2010 by Louis Farrakhan.", "answer": "<em><b> Nation of Islam</b></em> (accept<em><b> NOI</b></em>, do not accept or prompt on just \u201cIslam\u201d)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, George Gay was the only survivor of John Waldron\u2019s VT-8. The efforts of SBD Dauntless dive bombers proved more successful than the TBD Devastators, sinking the Hiryu, Soryu, and Kaga. A forty-eight hour repair of the carrier Yorktown enabled its decisive participation in this battle after damage suffered at the Battle of the Coral Sea. For ten points, name this turning point of the War in the Pacific, a June 1942 naval victory named for an island west of Hawaii.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Midway</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s role in the Soka Gakkai Buddhist movement may have influenced him to rename one of the Causeway Islands after Daisaku Ikeda. This man, who ordered the brutal execution of Hugo Spadafora, rose to power with Ruben Paredes after a plane crash at Cerro Marta killed the former leader of his country. Operation Just Cause ousted this leader, who was assaulted with rock music while hiding in the Vatican embassy. For ten points, name this 1980s-era dictator of Panama.", "answer": "Manuel (Antonio)<em><b> Noriega</b></em> Moreno", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In a letter to Jean-Jacques Rousseau, this thinker claimed he changed his name \u201cprimarily so as to cease to be confused with the poet Roi.\u201d [WAH] While spying on Frederick the Great during the War of the Austrian Succession, this man began working on his Philosophical Dictionary. This thinker mocked Leibniz\u2019s \u201coptimistic determinism\u201d in a philosophical satire. For ten points, name this French enlightenment thinker, the author of Candide.", "answer": "<em><b> Voltaire</b></em> (or Francois-Marie<em><b> Arouet</b></em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, an attempt by the Luftwaffe to gain control of the skies was known as Operation Bodenplatte. A city in the province of Liege was home to the Malmedy Massacre at this battle. The German goal of this battle was to reach north Belgium through the Ardennes Forest. A response to an ultimatum consisting only of the word \u201cNuts\u201d occurred at, for ten points, what 1944 World War Two battle popularly named for an anomaly in the German lines?", "answer": "Battle of the<em><b> Bulge</b></em> (accept<em><b> Ardennes Counteroffensive</b></em> prior to mention)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The phrase \u201cKollaa will hold\u201d originated during this war in which one side employed an encirclement strategy known as motti. A year after the conclusion of this conflict, the two central countries began the Continuation War. The Vainamoinen was a coastal defense vessel used by one navy during this war in which one side was commanded by Gustaf Mannerheim. Lasting from 1939 to 1940, for ten points, name this conflict that began with the Soviet invasion of Finland.", "answer": "<em><b> Winter War</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s aide, John Armstrong, was discovered to have been plotting the Newburgh Conspiracy to launch a military coup. In another plot, this man was forced to issue an apology for supporting the Conway (+) Cabal\u2019s attempts to unseat George Washington. This man\u2019s reputation was ruined after Johann de Kalb was killed under his command at (*)</b> Camden. This man had earlier risen to prominence after forcing John Burgoyne\u2019s surrender. For ten points, identify this general of the Continental Army who was victorious at Saratoga.", "answer": "Horatio<em><b> Gates</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This woman\u2019s lover, Alexei Razumovsky, was nicknamed the \u201cNight Emperor,\u201d and she is known for not executing a single person during her reign. This woman was described as the \u201cMessalina of the North\u201d by a rival monarch whom she fought in the (+) Seven Years\u2019War. This woman\u2019s reign saw many architectural projects including the near completion of a project criticized for \u201cgilded squalor,\u201d the Winter Palace. This woman took power by (*) </b>overthrowing Ivan VI in a coup after the death of Empress Anna. For ten points, name this daughter of Peter the Great, an Empress of Russia who was succeeded by Peter III.", "answer": "<em><b> Elizabeth</b></em> Petrovna (accept Y<em><b>elizaveta</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Gilbert Ellis suspected the namesake of this city of plotting to declare a king to be sane. The first African American real estate firm, Ideal Realty, was founded in this city. In 1781, Thomas Nelson, Jr. and Benjamin Harrison V fled to this city, which was targeted by (+) Banastre Tarleton, forcing Jack Jouett to make a midnight ride to save the Patriots. The Rotunda at the University of (*)</b> Virginia is located in this city, where protests were held to oppose removal of a Robert E. Lee statue. For ten points, name this city where in 2017 counter protestors were attacked by a car driver during the Unite the Right rally.", "answer": "<em><b> Charlottesville</b></em>, Virginia (prompt on \u201cC\u2019ville\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This political party was founded in 1912 by John Langalibalele Dube and presided over the Marikana massacre of 34 striking miners. This party passed \u201cfloor crossing\u201d legislation which allowed MPs to take their seat to a different party. Andrew (+) Feinstein resigned when this party moved against a probe of the Arms Deal. The military arm of this party, Spear of the Nation, was founded after the (*) </b> Sharpeville massacre. In 2017, leadership of this party was granted to Cyril Ramaphosa. For ten points, name this party that has led its nation since Nelson Mandela became President of South Africa.", "answer": "<em><b> African National Congress</b></em> (accept<em><b> ANC</b></em>) Page 9", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>Engineer Roger Boisjoly said that this person was the only public figure to support his ominous warnings. General Donald Kutyna revealed that this person discretely told him about failing O-rings on the (+) Challenger Space Shuttle. This person was part of NASA Astronaut Group 9 and helped develop the \u201cCanadarm\u201d robot. Facing many intrusive questions from the press such as \u201cWill the flight affect your internal organs?\u201d this astronaut became the first (*) </b> American to do what Valentina Tereshkova accomplished. For ten points, name this first American woman in space.", "answer": "Sally<em><b> Ride</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Miles Lampson convinced a holder of this position to allow a party he opposed take power between 1942 and 1944. The sister of a holder of this position became the first wife of Mohammad (+) Reza Shah. The Second Italo-Abyssinian War contributed to one holder of this position signing a 1936 treaty in his Zaafarana Palace. That holder of this position was preceded and succeeded by men named (*) </b> Fouad. A 1952 revolution saw the Free Officers Movement overthrow one holder of this position named Farouk. For ten points, name this royal position that was first claimed by Sultan Fouad I in 1922.", "answer": "<em><b> King</b></em> of<em><b> Egypt</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In one scene in this film the protagonist asks another man why he doesn\u2019t seem alarmed to which that man replies \u201cwould it help?\u201d A scene in this film sees the protagonist meet Wolfgang Vogel to discuss the arrest of an American student named (+) Frederic Pryor. The title of this film comes from a climactic scene occurring above the Havel River. The main character is an insurance lawyer tasked with defending a Russian captive named (*) </b>Rudolf Abel. Based on a book by Giles Whittell and ending with a prisoner exchange involving Francis Gary Powers, for ten points, name this 2015 Cold War film starring Tom Hanks.", "answer": "<em><b> Bridge of Spies</b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>The details of this event were almost certainly planned at the Little Green House on K Street. This event was made possible after its perpetrator had acquired property from Edwin (+) Denby. Congress\u2019s power to compel testimony was confirmed when the case McGrain v. Daugherty arose from this event. The first cabinet member to go to jail was imprisoned as a result of this event, because he had leased the Elk Hills at cut-rate prices in exchange for bribes. That man was Secretary of the (*)</b> Interior Albert Fall. For ten points, Navy oil reserves were the subject of what 1922 scandal that befell the Harding administration?", "answer": "<em><b> Teapot Dome</b></em> scandal Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This commander\u2019s Operation Pugilist forced an opposing army to establish a new position 60 kilometers away from the Mareth Line. Following a stalemate at a certain location, Claude Auchinleck was replaced by this man, who won a later battle at that location. This man lost the (+) Race to Messina during the Allied Invasion of Sicily to U.S. commander George Patton. This leader of the Eighth Army won a decisive victory at the (*)</b> Second Battle of El Alamein. For ten points, name this British general who was instrumental in securing an Allied victory in the North African Campaign.", "answer": "Bernard Law<em><b> Montgomery</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}